ABDUL QADIR

Mechanical Engineer (MEP)



aqanwar97@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/abdul-gadir-anwar-789838150



+966597667140

Location: Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

Summary

A **Mechanical Engineer** with 6 years of experience as Technical and Design engineering knowledge in commercial and residential MEP projects. Backed by profound knowledge of Calculation and Codes. Coordinate Project design with architects, engineers, and developers, finalizing Scheme, Concept report and Detail design for issuing Tender drawing, BOQ and documents. Resolving RFI and site related queries. Targeting challenging assignments across HVAC, Fire Protection & Plumbing, Wet utilities.

Transferable IQAMA and Driving License available.

Saudi Council of Engineer, Membership ID: 987310

Experience

Mechanical Technical Engineer

Alfanar Projects

MAY 2024 - Present

- Design review and update shop drawing in compliance with authority and international standards.
- Reviewing the design in compliance with stakeholder requirements in an efficient, economical manner and include Value Engineering of Material submittal proposed by supplier.
- Perform Calculation for Mechanical service for HVAC laod, PLUMBING and FIRE system.
- Attending Client & contractor Coordination queries and meetings.

Mechanical Technical Engineer

FirstFix Saudi Arabia

March 2023 - April 2024

- Working on Shaura Island as Technical Design Engineer, My role here is to Look after Engineering requirement of construction by checking and issuing Shop drawings, Technical Data for Material submittals with various suppliers required in Mechanical scope and Procure material for site.
- Coordinate with Construction manager, Site Engineer and consultants to ensure all HVAC Infrastructure / Deep Drainage Drawings, OIL, IIL, CL are according to Shop drawing / IFC of wet utilities.
- Worked on the Red Sea Development project as a Mechanical Technical Engineer for Villa and Hotels on Island.
- Attend meetings with stakeholders and discuss upcoming Submissions, Challenges.
- Generate RFI based on drawings and Submittals based on HVAC, Fire and Plumbing.
- Understanding Requirements of Architects, Red Sea Global, and other consultants and issuing Shop drawings.

Mechanical Engineer- MEP

Buro Happold INDIA

Oct 2021 - Apr 2023

- Design and analysis of Mechanical systems such as HVAC system design, Fire Protection layout and Plumbing system for commercial and Residential Building which includes.
- Water supply-demand and drainage flow calculation using different plumbing codes/standards as NBC, IPC, ASPE, BS, etc.
- Plumbing system design, complete solution from the water supply, drainage network

- design to selection of pumps (knowledge of pump curve, characteristics).
- Tank capacity and pump room design, Storm drainage calculation, Equipment selection like booster pumps, circulating pumps, oil interceptors, and other plumbing equipment.
- HVAC load estimation on carrier HAP software, Fresh air calculation, chilled water network designing and sizing, piping layout for Air conditioning, calculate duct friction losses.
- Strong ability to review design development independently.
- Drafting of various models, layouts as per projects need using AutoCAD/Revit.
- Documentation work such as Bill of quantities, quantity takeoff, and preparation of equipment schedule.
- Coordinate with Interior Architects and understand there requirements for MEP services.

Mechanical Design Engineer- HVAC

DesignTree Service Consultants Pvt Ltd

Aug 2019 - Oct 2021 (2 years 3 months)

- Worked as a Design Engineer in a SMEP Consultancy.
- Well aware with the HVAC International and National Codes which are widely used such as ASHRAE NBC, ECBC.
- Preparing all the tender documents and drawings and ensuring they are in line with the project and client's requirements concluded in the early stages of a project.
- Attending design review meetings and coordination meetings with Architects, clients, contractors and other engineering consultants.
- Performing detailed calculations like heating/cooling load calculation, ventilation calculation, preparing schematics, ducting & CHW/LTHW piping design.
- · Conducting site visits and mechanical inspections
- Pressurization calculations for Staircase and Lift Lobby as per NBC(2016).
- Basement Ventilation Calculation for Zoning, Exhaust and Fresh Air by using •Mechanical ventilation as per standard.
- · Unit selection and Configuration as per the requirement.
- HVAC Designing of Residential and Commercial buildings
- Preparation of final design drawings for various projects.

HVAC Design Intern

Sterling and Wilson India

Jan 2019 - Apr 2019 (4 months)

•Assessing staff requirements at each work stage, agreeing these with the project manager and being able to manage single disciplinary and multi-disciplinary projects.

HVAC Course

JM MEP ACADEMY

May 2018 - Jul 2018 (3 months)

- ·Heat Load calculation
- Duct routing and duct sizing (Drafting)
- ·Basement ventilation calculations and exhaust system designing
- Chilled water piping sizing
- Estimating and costing

Education

Integral University, Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh, INDIA

Bachelor of Technology. Mechanical Engineering 2015 - 2019

Symbiosis Institute of Management Studies

Master of Business Administration - MBA, Project Management 2020 - 2022
Pursuing in Distance education.

International Indian School Jeddah,KSA High School, Science

2007 - 2015

Licenses & Certifications

Autodesk AutoCAD User Certification - CETPA Infotech Pvt. ltd.

Autodesk Revit Certified Professional Certification - Udemy

Skills

Equipment Sizing • Engineering Design • Detailed Design • Mechanical, Electrical, and Plumbing (MEP) • Revit • Computer-Aided Design (CAD) • HVAC Design • Carrier HAP • HVAC • Project Management



Membership no.:987310





عضوية رقم:987310

In accordance with the Regulations of Saudi Council of Engineers by Royal Decree M/36 Date 26/9/1423H and the Engineering Professions Practice Regulation by Royal Decreee M/36 Date19/4/1438 H. SCE has approved:

اســـتناداً إلى نظام الهيئة الســعودية للمهندســين الصادر بالمرســوم الملكي رقم م/٣٦ وتاريخ ١٤٢٣/٩/٢٦هـ ونظام مزاولة المهن الهندسية الصادر بالمرســـوم الملكي م/٣٦ وتاريـــخ ١٤٣٨/٤/١٩هـ ولائحته التنفيذية فقد قررت الهيئة اعتماد:

,19jl ,7lë +7?c

Membership Category: Engineering Technologist

Specialization: Mechanical Engineering Technology

Membership Start Date: 11/19/2023



ABDUL QADIR ANWAR

jäï u7jga :**i9aJl jė**

ĩSijlSiaJl TjgJl ĩjäï **ڀُلَا**

11/19/2023 :i9aJI il7? i,li

This Certification is valid until

19 November 2024

1446 'J9ĕl И7lac 18

هذه الشهادة صالحة إلى تاريخ

Secretary General الأمين العام فيسد ėibJJI7?aJI ėį ¡? □[jJI7?c ., / ėJSaJI